A Guide to the Anne Griswold Tyng Architectural Collection, 1969-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Anne Griswold Tyng Architectural Collection, 1969-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-049
1.5 cu. ft.
Born in 1920 in Lushan, Jiangxi province, China where her parents were living as missionaries, Tyng was an architect, professor, and design theorist best known for her collaborations with Louis I. Kahn. Studied at Radcliffe-Harvard (1942), received her Masters at Harvard Graduate School of Design (1944), and PhD in Architecture from University of Pennsylvania (1975). She specialized in space frame architecture and mathematics. Tyng designed and built the first totally triangulated space-frame house for hollowed out living space. Collection consist of publications, exhibit materials, and biographical material.
Tyng, Anne Griswold, 1920-2011
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Anne Griswold Tyng Architectural Collection was donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture in 2000. Additional materials were donated in March 2004.
Biographical Note
Anne Griswold Tyng (July 14, 1920- December 27, 2011) was an architect and professor. She is best known for her three decade collaboration and partnership with Louis I. Kahn. Tyng graduated with a B. Arch from the Radcliffe-Harvard College (1942) and later received her Masters from Harvard Graduate School of Design (1944). She had the unique experience of being at the heart of three architectural movements: "Bauhaus Renaissance" at Harvard, Buckminster Fuller's exploration of innovative geometry and high technology, and Louis Kahn's synthesis of geometry and humanism.
After working at Stonorov and Kahn Architects (1945-1947), Office of Louis I. Kahn FAIA (1947-1974), Anne Giswold Tyng, FAIA (1949-1999), and Louis I. Kahn and Anne G. Tyng Associated Architects (1951-1974) Tyng became a professor. She spent much of her later career teaching architecture at the University of Pennsylvania where she received her PhD in 1975. Tyng is the recipient of numerous honors, has participated in 25 exhibits, published 27 articles, and presented 68 lectures. Tyng's influence on Kahn's work was finally recognized in 2010 when The Institute of Contemporary Art held a retrospective exhibition of her work.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of files and drawings that relate to Tyng's work as an architectural designer and theorist. It includes professional writings, drawings, and biographical material. The majority of the collection consists of photocopies of drawings from Tyng's weekend project at Virginia Tech titled "The Creative Experience' held March 1999.
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Artwork, 3 ink and pencil sketches, undated
  - Sketch of arched-cylindrical version of cut-away columns (Box 1)
  - Room arrangement proposed for building as built (not used) (Box 1)
  - Large meeting-dining spaces made by corbelling pre-cast squares and unifying structure with 3 dimensional flying buttresses (Box 1)
- Biographical Information (Box 1)
- Presentations
  - Two on Two at the Octagon (Washington D.C., January-March 1979) (Box 1)
  - PASCAL in 3D: How the Ball Bounces, Probability in Action (University of Pennsylvania, February 1984) (Box 1)
  - The Creative Experience (Virginia Tech, March 1999) Display Materials and Flyer (Box 1, Box 2)
    Historical Note
    Anne Griswold Tyng led a Weekend Project titled 'The Creative Experience' at Virginia Tech from March 19-March 21, 1999. The weekend's activities included a lecture, exhibit, and reception.
    Scope and Content
    Material contains a flyer advertising the event, photocopies of works included in the exhibit, and a mounted photograph from the exhibit. (6 folders).
  - Urbanism at the Margins (University of Pennsylvania, March 1999) (Box 2)
- Professional Writings
  - Geometric Extension of Consciousness, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Crafting Space or Tossing Dice- Platonic Playthings of Baby Bacchus, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Seeing Order- Systems and Symbols, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Resonance Between Eye and Archetype, 1983 (Box 1)
  - From Muse to Heroine, Toward a Visible Creative Identity, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Synthesis of a Traditional House with a Space Frame, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Inner Vision Toward an Architecture of Organic Humanism, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Random Play to Ordered Archetype, undated (Box 1)